Guide to the Miracle House Records 1990-2014 MS 3098
New-York Historical Society
Miracle House records
1990-2014
New-York Historical Society
Miracle House (New York, N.Y.)
MS 3098
8 Linear feet in 3 flat boxes, 3 cartons, and 1 flat file folder
127 Gigabytes
This collection contains material from the records of Miracle House, a charity that provided housing, meals, and support services to patients and their caregivers traveling to New York City for medical treatment. The collection consists primarily of records related to fundraising, publicity, and routine business operations.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 2 series:
Series I. Digital Files
Series II. Other Records
Biographical / Historical
Miracle House was founded in 1990 in response to the AIDS crisis to provide affordable temporary housing, free meals and support services to patients and caregivers of people living with AIDS in New York City. In 1997, Miracle House expanded its services to include cancer patients, and in 2005, began to include patients and their caregivers traveling to New York City for any medically related treatment options, procedures, or consultations. Starting with one studio apartment on Manhattan's upper west side, by 2004 Miracle House was operating five apartments, providing a total capacity of 5,475 rooms per year. Citing difficulties with rising costs of the New York City rental market as well as increasing administrative costs, Miracle House ceased operation in 2014.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Miracle House, 2014.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of records related to fundraising, publicity, and routine business operations such as financial records, annual reports, budgets, and Board meeting minutes. There is also documentation about clinical trials taking place in New York City, client reports and testimonials, newsletters, and shopping lists for the various apartments. There are numerous event files such as photos, flyers, press releases, mailers, sponsor forms, spreadsheets of expenses, letters to donors and other marketing materials.
Fund raising.; Nonprofit Organizations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publicity.; Digital file formats.; Digital images.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Series I. Digital Files, 127 Gigabytes
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes digital files of records related to fundraising, publicity, and routine business operations such as financial records, annual reports, budgets, and Board minutes. There is also documentation about clinical trials taking place in New York City, client reports and testimonials, newsletters, and shopping lists for the various apartments. The library cannot provide access to all digital files due to file corruption, lack of required software, and/or system specifications. A full manifest of the individual files comprising the series is available from the reference librarian on request.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Digital Files
  Subseries I.B. CDs and DVDs.
  - Subseries I.A: Digital Files, 1991-2014, 80 Gigabytes (56,379 Files, 4,091 Folders)
    Digital content was delivered by the donor on a 1TB Seagate external hard drive and a duplicate 1TB Seagate internal hard drive. Both drives contained all files and directories from the organization's server (56,379 Files, 4,091 Folders). The content consists primarily of records related to fundraising, publicity, and routine business operations.
    - Digital files from hard drive (Folder 1-116)
    - Hard drives (2). RESTRICTED (Offsite-box 6)
      This box holds the hard drive and its duplicate from which the above files were extracted. It is retained for back-up purposes only and is restricted from use.
  - Subseries I.B: CDs and DVDs, 1991-2013, 2004-2012; 47 Gigabytes (24,285 Files in 1,161 Folders across 116 CDs).
    This subseries contains files from CDs and DVDs received from the donor. The content consists primarily of records related to fundraising and publicity, as well as records of routine business operations and file backups. Represented events include Miracle Paddle, Cocktails by the Bay, the Diversity Players of Harlem health fair, Miracle House Mid and Year-End Appeals, and Tea-quila! Party, a fundraiser held in Pines, Fire Island and referred to as Pines throughout the collection. Documents include numerous photos, flyers, press releases, mailers, graphics files for flyers, sponsor forms, spreadsheets of expenses, letters to donors and other marketing materials.
    138 discs were received, but 22 discs were not imaged because they were either duplicates or contained copyrighted music. 116 discs were imaged to the ISO format and files were exported from the disk images. The discs were received in one wallet and some loose in one box. Each disc was numbered based on the order starting with the discs in the wallet, and any title or information written on the discs was transcribed to the filename. Each entry in this series represents one disc.
    - 1_MiraclePaddle06MiscFiles (Folder 1)
    - 2_Events2006 (Folder 2)
    - 3_Events06-07MarketingMaterials (Folder 3)
    - 4_2006Events (Folder 4)
    - 5_Pines 2007 (Folder 5)
    - 6_[DiscError]Cabaret06 (Folder 6)
    - 7_MiracleGiftsAssets_YearEndAppeal07 (Folder 7)
    - 8_Event06-07Continued (Folder 8)
    - 9_2007EventMarketingMaterial (Folder 9)
    - 10_MHDVD_Auction2007 (Folder 10)
    - 11_[illegible]FilesPics (Folder 11)
    - 12_MiracleHouseMem09Logos (Folder 12)
    - 13_YE Appeal 07 (Folder 13)
    - 14_FalsActors (Folder 14)
    - 15_MHCameraPix_Event (Folder 15)
    - 16_Throckmorton_Masks (Folder 16)
    - 17_MiracleHouseCocktailParty07 (Folder 17)
    - 18_CocktailsByTheBay07_pics (Folder 18)
    - 19_MiracleHouseStillsFrom2007Kickoff (Folder 19)
    - 20_Miracle House AIDS Walk 2008 (Folder 20)
    - 21_2008MiracleHouseKickoffOriginals (Folder 21)
    - 22_PinesParty2008 (Folder 22)
    - 23_MiracleHouseVolunteers2009 (Folder 23)
    - 24_MHImpressionism (Folder 24)
    - 25_MiracleHouseSummerBlastoff2009PicturesbyLKennedy_1of2 (Folder 25)
    - 26_MiracleHouseSummerBlastoff2009PicturesbyLKennedy_2of2 (Folder 26)
    - 27_MH Memorial Day (Folder 27)
    - 28_Cocktails BTB 2006 (Folder 28)
    - 29_CBTB 07-25-2009_1of2 (Folder 29)
    - 30_CBTB 07-25-2009_2of2 (Folder 30)
    - 31_MH party 12_08 photos (Folder 31)
    - 32_MiracleHouse_PM_ (Folder 32)
    - 33_MIRACLEHOUSE_S_0 (Folder 33)
    - 34_CBTB 10 Low Res (Folder 34)
    - 35_CBTB 10 Hi Res (Folder 35)
    - 36_20YearsFundraiser_7-31-10 (Folder 36)
    - 37_CocktailsByTheBay_7-30-11 (Folder 37)
    - 38_Cocktails by the bay 2011 (Folder 38)
    - 39_MIRACLEHOUSE_PMC_5-28-11_Bulk1 (Folder 39)
    - 40_MIRACLEHOUSE_PMC_5-28-11_Bulk2 (Folder 40)
    - 41_MiracleHouse22ndAnnualSummerKickoff_5-26-12_1of2 (Folder 41)
    - 42_MiracleHouse22ndAnnualSummerKickoff_5-26-12_2of2 (Folder 42)
    - 43_MHFoundersPinesParty91_photo (Folder 43)
    - 44_Miracle House 2007-10-10 (Folder 44)
    - 45_Guests2 (Folder 45)
    - 46_Miracle House - b_w and color (Folder 46)
    - 47_ChadAustinVolunteer (Folder 47)
    - 48_EmilysWebsiteFiles_CBTB08Apt08 (Folder 48)
    - 49_MHApartmentPics7-06 (Folder 49)
    - 50_MiracleHouseFeb07JoTragakiKIPCheneyBakerCohen (Folder 50)
    - 51_miracle house_BrunchAndCityScenes (Folder 51)
    - 52_MH_History_pics (Folder 52)
    - 53_MH_pictures_apt_clients_2004-2008 (Folder 53)
    - 54_MIRACLE HOUSE AD (Folder 54)
    - 55_MiracleHousePhotos10-08-09 (Folder 55)
    - 56_Miracle House Color (Folder 56)
    - 57_PictureArchives07_PlumTV (Folder 57)
    - 58_MiracleHousePhotosClientsVolunteers10-08-09 (Folder 58)
    - 59_Italian family pcitures (Folder 59)
    - 60_AmyChanos2-22-10 (Folder 60)
    - 61_Miracle House by Sandro Lamberti (Folder 61)
    - 62_Newsletters07 (Folder 62)
    - 63_[DiscError]Plum_MorningNoonNightShow_20060528 (Folder 63)
    - 64_Plum_MorningNoonNightShow_20060729 (Folder 64)
    - 65_Plum_MorningNoonNightShow_20070527 (Folder 65)
    - 66_OldCampaignPosters (Folder 66)
    - 67_RyanChristiQuigley9-13-06 (Folder 67)
    - 68_MiracleHouse_5A_DanAndPat (Folder 68)
    - 69_MarketingMaterials (Folder 69)
    - 70_[DiscError]MiracleHouse (Folder 70)
    - 71_MiracleHouseonNBCNews (Folder 71)
    - 72_mh poster (Folder 72)
    - 73_Tri-fold Brochure (Folder 73)
    - 74_MiracleHouseOnNBCNews (Folder 74)
    - 75_[DiscError]MiracleHouse_Spring07Newsletter (Folder 75)
    - 76_BackupMH_Events2003-2006 (Folder 76)
    - 77_AnnualReport2006 (Folder 77)
    - 78_AnnualReport2006MiscFiles (Folder 78)
    - 79_MiracleHouseBackup (Folder 79)
    - 80_WelcomePackageFitch (Folder 80)
    - 81_MiracleHouse12-07Fitch (Folder 81)
    - 82_MHBackupQABackup (Folder 82)
    - 83_QBSJan-Mar07 (Folder 83)
    - 84_QBSApril-June07 (Folder 84)
    - 85_Backups_JaniceHaleyJune07 (Folder 85)
    - 86_MHBackupTrifoldBrochureNewslettersPaddle06TxtFiles (Folder 86)
    - 87_ExEmployeeBackup (Folder 87)
    - 88_MiracleHouse501c3Files (Folder 88)
    - 89_MHNewWebsiteFilesAndDesign (Folder 89)
    - 90_MiracleHouseAnnualReport2008 (Folder 90)
    - 91_MH T-Shirt (Folder 91)
    - 92_MiracleHouse_10-7-10_SandroLamberti (Folder 92)
    - 93_20YrMontage (Folder 93)
    - 94_MiracleHouseSandroLambertiPhotography (Folder 94)
    - 95_MHClientsAndStaff_10-6-12_SandroLanberti (Folder 95)
    - 96_MiracleHouse_7-25-11_SandroLamberti (Folder 96)
    - 97_MiracleHouseElbaJorgeLeslieRollins_SandroLamberti (Folder 97)
    - 98_MiracleHouse_HopeAwayFromHome1998 (Folder 98)
    - 99_MiracleHouseReception_HomeOfMarilynSuder (Folder 99)
    - 100_ThrockmortonFineArt (Folder 100)
    - 101_InternetSections (Folder 101)
    - 102_MiracleHousePostcard (Folder 102)
    - 103_AngelFlight2003 (Folder 103)
    - 104_MIRACLE HOUSE AD (Folder 104)
    - 105_MiracleHouse_HopeAwayFromHome2005 (Folder 105)
    - 106_YearEndAppealForMiracleHouse2004 (Folder 106)
    - 107_MH_MEM_INUITE_04_05-06-04 (Folder 107)
    - 108_MH_MEM_INUITE_04_05-07-04 (Folder 108)
    - 109_MHAnnualReport04_8-31-04 (Folder 109)
    - 110_MiracleHouseOnNBCNews (Folder 110)
    - 111_LifetimeTVMiracleHouse_10-7-2004 (Folder 111)
    - 112_MiracleHouse (Folder 112)
    - 113_MHSpringAppeal08Files (Folder 113)
    - 114_MHAnnualReport08TextFiles (Folder 114)
    - 115_MHAnnualReport08Pictures (Folder 115)
    - 116_MiracleHouse10-25-13SandroLambertiPhotography (Folder 116)
    - CDs/DVDs. RESTRICTED (Offsite-box 6)
      This box holds the CDs and DVDs from which the above files were extracted. They were retained for back-up purposes and are restricted from being opened to access the digital files. However, the physical media itself can be requested and examined for context.
- Series II. Other Records, 1990-2014; 7 Linear feet in 3 flat boxes, 2 cartons, and 1 flat file folder
  The series includes the formats other than digital files in the collection. This principally includes publicity and fundraising event brochures, announcements, invitations, programs, newsletters, and other similar print matter. There are several chronologically sequenced scrapbooks that trace the organization's history from 1990-2010 with photographs, print matter, news articles, and the like. There are guest comment books and many letters of appreciation from guests, extracts of which were often published under the heading "love letters" in Miracle House's newsletters, which are also in the series.
  The series is arranged by format.
  - "Love letters" [Letters of appreciation] (8 folders), 1995-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Guest comment books (3 folders), 1996-2014 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - "Miracle House Update" [newsletter], 1992-2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fundraising: Summer Kickoff programs (2 folders), 2008-2014 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Also includes print-outs of some photos from the 2009-12 galas.
  - Fundraising: Bed & Breakfast Campaign, Phase II, 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes background on the campaign, talking points, budget, etc.
  - Publicity materials, 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Publicity materials (2 folders), circa 2009-2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17-18)
    Includes, among other documents, brochures with annual reports for 2009 and 2011, publicity pieces tied to the 20th anniversary (2010), and Miracle House's dinner menu at the Pompon Diner and printed directions to various hospitals.
  - Publicity: "At Home" magazine article, 2004 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    Holds the Fall 2004 issue of "At Home" magazine with article "Miracle on 43rd Street" article concerning the design of Miracle House's rooms (pages 99-104).
  - Proposed property purchase, 2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    Documents related to the proposed acquisition by Miracle House of the former Rice High School building at 74 West 124th Street.
  - Miracle House lapel pins, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photograph album, 1990s? (Offsite-box 1)
    Album includes uncaptioned photographs; they appear to be of various staff events, such as Halloween and other holiday gatherings.
  - Videocassettes. RESTRICTED, 2006, undated (Offsite-box 1)
    4 cassettes: "Miracle House, Nita Pippins, 4/26/06" in 3 parts on 3 cassettes; and "Miracle House: Hope Away From Home." The videos are restricted from use because of their fragility and N-YHS's lack of equipment to play them. For further information, contact the manuscripts curator at manuscripts@nyhistory.org.
  - Hard drives (2) RESTRICTED (Offsite-box 1)
    The hard drives are for back-up contingency purposes only and may not be used except by digital processing staff. The files from the drives are available for research; see Series I.
  - Scrapbooks (2), 1992-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 1-2)
  - Scrapbooks (3), 1990-2000 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 1-3)
    Box holds the annual scrapbook for 2000 plus a two scrapbook set commemorating the organization's 10th anniversary with photos and other documents spanning 1990-2000.
  - Scrapbooks (2), 2001-2002, 2006 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 1-2)
  - Scrapbooks (4), 2007-2010 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 1-4)
    The 2008 scrapbook holds a DVD of the memorial Mass for Helen Sweetser at Church of St. Ignatius Loyola.
  - Oversize items, 1990-1994 (Folder OS-Small)
    Includes the following items:
    * Photograph of AIDS awareness ribbon composed of roses. Photographer: Susumu Sato, gift from Sato to Miracle House. Signed, dated 1994, numbered 9/40.
    * Drawing, front elevation of 156 West 95th Street, initialed G.H., dated 7/5/91.
    * Gouache on Mylar, graphic for the Hamptons Hoe-Down, first fundraiser in Hamptons, 1991.
    * Photograph, at 1st fundraiser in Pines, 1990.
    * 4 posters, with varying content, on the theme of "I believe in miracles."